A Guide to the Merrill D. Peterson Papers
Special Collections Department, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library, #12807
Merrill D. Peterson Papers 1852-1993
University of Virginia. Library. Special Collections Dept. Alderman Library University of Virginia Charlottesville, Virginia 22903 USA
12807
ca. 16,000 items
Merrill D. Peterson
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
The collection is a gift from Professor Emeritus Merrill D. Peterson
Biographical Sketch
Merrill Daniel Peterson, one of the nation's most honored and respected historians on the age of Jefferson has been Thomas Jefferson Memorial Foundation Professor Emeritus at the University of Virginia in Charlottesville since his retirement in 1987. He was born on March 31, 1921, the son of William Oscar and Alice Dwinell (Merrill) Peterson in Manhattan, Kansas. Peterson received his bachelor's degree from the University of Kansas in 1943 and earned a Ph.D. in the history of American civilization from Harvard in 1950. He taught at Harvard, Brandeis and Princeton Universities. At Brandeis, he was the Harry S. Truman Professor and dean of students before he joined the University of Virginia faculty in 1962, succeeding another noted Jefferson scholar, Dumas Malone, as Thomas Jefferson Memorial Foundation Professor of History. He later served as chairman of the University's Corcoran Department of History and dean of the faculty of arts and sciences.
Peterson is the author of
The Jefferson Image in the American Mind
, for which he won the Bancroft Prize in American History and the Thomas Jefferson Memorial Foundation's gold medal in 1961. His other publications include:
Major Crises in American History
Democracy, Liberty and Property: The State Constitutional Conventions of the 1820's
Thomas Jefferson and the New Nation: A Biography
James Madison: A Biography in His Own Words
Adams and Jefferson: A Revolutionary Dialogue
, which resulted from his Lamar lectures delivered at Mercer University in 1975
Olive Branch and Sword: The Compromise of 1833
, from his Fleming lectures at Louisiana State University in 1980 and
The Great Triumvirate: Webster, Clay and Calhoun
, from his work as a National Endowment for the Humanities fellow at Chapel Hill, North Carolina in 1980-1981. Peterson is also editor of six books in American History including:
Thomas Jefferson: A Profile
The Portable Thomas Jefferson
Thomas Jefferson Writings
Thomas Jefferson: A Reference Biography
The Virginia Statute of Religious Freedom: Its Evolution and Consequences in American History
and
Visitors to Monticello
.
In 1976, Peterson received a doctor of humane letters degree from Washington College and was named a fellow of the American Academy of Arts and Sciences in 1980. He is a member of Phi Beta Kappa, the American Historical Association and the University of Virginia's honorary Raven Society. He has served on the board of the Virginia Foundation for the Humanities and Public Policy for whom he planned a major symposium commemorating the bicentennial of the Virginia Statute for Religious Freedom. In 1987, he was project director for a year-long colloquium on the humanities and the American people in conjunction with the National Endowment for the Humanities. Other organizational memberships and fellowships include: the Thomas Jefferson Memorial Foundation, the Virginia Historical Society, the Southern Historical Association, the Society of American Historians, the American Antiquarian Society and the Massachusetts Historical Society, the Guggenheim fellowship, the Center for Advanced Studies in Behavioral Sciences fellowship and the Poynter fellowship at Indiana University. In 1974, Peterson served as scholar-in-residence at the Bellagio Study Center in Italy and, in 1975, on the faculty of the Salzburg Seminar in American Studies in Vienna, Austria. In 1988-1989, he lectured on U.S. History at the National University of Ireland in Dublin as a Fulbright Scholar and in 1993, President Clinton named him chairman of the Thomas Jefferson Commemoration Commission.
Scope and Content
The collection contains ca. 16,000 items (15 shelf feet) consisting of department and personal communications with historians, university colleagues, students, friends and academic organizations throughout the United States and from around the world (grouped under Correspondence); academic, lecture and professional organization records associated with Peterson's activities while at Harvard, Brandeis and the University of Virginia(grouped under Academia); writings, including TMss, drafts, notes and communications with publishers relating to the books and articles Peterson authored (grouped under Publications) and an assortment of newsclippings; pamphlets; photographs (14 items); reprints; unpublished MDP writings and background material including, MDP notes, bibliographical listings and items relating to the alleged Thomas Jefferson and Sally Hemings relationship (grouped under Miscellany).
In addition, outside of this collection under related accessions, are a collection of photocopied letters of Calhoun, Clay and Webster which Peterson used in his research for The
Great Triumvirate
[Mss #10718] and a tape recorded lecture "Jefferson, the Enlightenment and the Revolution" which he delivered at a University of Virginia student forum on October 8, 1973 [Mss #8033-b,-c].
Container List
- Group I: Correspondence
  - Correspondence, 1949-1967; (6 folders) (Box Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1968-1972; (6 folders) (Box Box 2)
  - Correspondence, 1973-1974; (6 folders) (Box Box 3)
  - Correspondence, 1975-1976; (7 folders) (Box Box 4)
  - Correspondence, 1977-1979; (7 folders) (Box Box 5)
  - Correspondence, 1980-1981; (6 folders) (Box Box 6)
  - Correspondence, 1982-1984; (7 folders) (Box Box 7)
  - Correspondence, 1985-1986; (6 folders) (Box Box 8)
  - Correspondence, 1987-1989; (7 folders) (Box Box 9)
- Group II: Academia
  - Brandeis University
    - American Civilization Committee (Merrill D. Peterson), 1958-1962 (Box Box 10)
    - American Civilization Course Lecture Notes, 1953-1955, n.d.; (2 folders) (Box Box 10)
    - "American System, 1815-1832", 1959 (Box Box 10)
    - Applications and Grants, 1954-1962 (Box Box 10)
    - Course Material and Reprints, 1951 (Box Box 10)
    - History Department--Memoranda, 1959-1962 (Box Box 10)
    - History Department--Personnel, 1958-1962, n.d. (Box Box 10)
    - "Perspectives in American History" (Merrill D. Peterson and L.W. Levy), 1951-1952 (Box Box 10)
    - Speech Material, ca.1960's (Box Box 11)
    - Teaching Appointments, 1954-1963 (Box Box 11)
  - Harvard University
    - Ph.D. Thesis--"The Jefferson Image in the American Mind, 1826-1861", 1950 (Box Box 12)
    - Student Class Notes, 1946 (Box Box 12)
  - University of Virginia
    - American Council of Learned Societies (James Settle), 1968-1970 (Box Box 13)
    - American Historical Association (Nominating Committee), 1967-1969 (Box Box 13)
    - "American Revolution", Oxford History of the United States, 1963-1965 (Box Box 13)
    - Assembly of Professors, 1964-1976, n.d.; (2 folders) (Box Box 13)
    - Bicentennial of the American Revolution--Classroom Project, 1974-1975 (Box Box 13)
    - Bicentennial of the American Revolution-- Federalist, 1976, 1971-1975 (Box Box 13)
    - Bicentennial of the American Revolution--National Committee, 1971-1976; (3 folders) (Box Box 14)
    - Bicentennial of the American Revolution--National Gallery of Art Exhibit, 1971-1974 (Box Box 14)
    - Bicentennial of the American Revolution--Organization of American Historians (Bicentennial Committee), 1973 (Box Box 14)
    - Bicentennial of the American Revolution--Personal Memorabilia, 1971-1979, n.d.; (2 folders) (Box Box 14)
    - Bicentennial of the American Revolution--Smithsonian National Portrait Gallery, 1968-1970 (Box Box 15)
    - Bicentennial of the American Revolution--Virginia Bicentennial Booklets, 1970-1971 (Box Box 15)
    - Center for Advanced Studies in Behavioral Sciences, 1966-1968 (Box Box 15)
    - Colloquium on the Humanities and the American People, 1987-1988, n.d.; (3 folders) (Box Box 15)
    - Conferences--American Philosophical Society (November, 1972) (Box Box 16)
    - Conferences--Historians and Teachers of Social Studies (February, 1971), 1970-1971 (Box Box 16)
    - Conferences--National Archives (November, 1973), 1972-1973 (Box Box 16)
    - Conferences--National Center for Scientific Research (February, 1978) (Box Box 16)
    - Conferences--National Historical Society (November, 1970) (Box Box 16)
    - Conferences--Virginia State Department of Education (March, 1970), 1969-1970 (Box Box 16)
    - Doar House Judiciary Committee Project, 1974-1975 (Box Box 16)
    - Federalist Papers Reexamined Project, 1976, n.d. (Box Box 16)
    - History Department--Chaired Professors, 1975-1976 (Box Box 16)
    - History Department--Chairmanship, 1978 (Box Box 16)
    - History Department--Miscellaneous Communications, 1975-1977, n.d. (Box Box 16)
    - Institute of Early American History and Culture, 1965-1968 (Box Box 16)
    - Lecture Notes, 1961-1968, n.d.; (1 of 9 folders) (Box Box 16)
    - Lecture Notes, 1961-1968, n.d.; (2-9 of 9 folders) (Box Box 17)
    - Legal History Programs for History and Law Students, 1967-1972 (Box Box 18)
    - Malone, Dumas--Notes and Memoirs, 1981-1987, n.d.; (3 folders) (Box Box 18)
    - Miscellaneous Administrative Records, 1972-1987, n.d. (Box Box 18)
    - National Endowment for the Humanities, 1966-1983; (1-2 of 3 folders) (Box Box 18)
    - National Endowment for the Humanities, 1966-1983; (3 of 3 folders) (Box Box 19)
    - National Trust for Historic Preservation--Montpelier, 1986-1988 (Box Box 19)
    - Notes on Virginia Project, 1981-1982 (Box Box 19)
    - Organization of American Historians, 1968-1975; (2 folders) (Box Box 19)
    - Papers of James Madison, 1971-1987 (Box Box 19)
    - Papers of James Madison--Editor Applicants, 1986-1986; (2 folders) (Box Box 19)
    - Papers of John Marshall--Advisory Committee, 1966-1970 (Box Box 19)
    - Pine Knot--Theodore Roosevelt's Virginia Retreat, 1907-1992 (Box Box 19)
    - Phi Beta Kappa Book Awards--Emerson Award Committee, 1982-1984 (Box Box 19)
    - Reviews--Merrill D. Peterson, 1951-1964; (2 folders) (Box Box 20)
    - Reviews in American History--Editorial Board (Merrill D. Peterson), 1972-1975 (Box Box 20)
    - Rockefeller Foundation--Bellagio Study and Conference Center, 1973-1977 (Box Box 20)
    - Salzburg Seminars in American Studies, 1973-1975 (Box Box 20)
    - Simkins Prize in Southern History, 1972-1974 (Box Box 20)
    - Speech: remarks at "sympathy for Selma" event at the Rotunda, 1965 March 17 (Box Box 20)
    - "Three Revolutions of Thomas Jefferson"--Film Documentary, 1974-1976, n.d.; (1-3 of 6 folders) (Box Box 20)
    - "Three Revolutions of Thomas Jefferson"--Film Documentary, 1974-1976, n. d.; (4-6 of 6 folders) (Box Box 21)
    - Thomas Jefferson Memorial Foundation and The Jefferson Foundation, 1972-1991; (2 folders) (Box Box 21)
    - United States Information Agency (USIA), 1974-1976 (Box Box 21)
    - University Press of Virginia, 1977-1988; (3 folders) (Box Box 22)
    - Virginia Statute for Religious Freedom--Virginia Foundation for the Humanities, 1983-1985, n.d. (Box Box 22)
    - Williamsburg International Assembly, 1962-1967 (Box Box 22)
- Group III: Publications
  - Adams and Jefferson: A Revolutionary Dialogue, 1976-1981, n.d.; (4 folders) (Box Box 23)
  - Articles (by Merrill D. Peterson)-- Encyclopedia of the American Constitution, 1979-1984, n.d. (Box Box 23)
  - Articles (by Merrill D. Peterson)-- Encyclopedia of World Biography, 1969-1970 (Box Box 23)
  - Articles (by Merrill D. Peterson)-- World of Jefferson, Weidenfeld and Nicolson, 1972-1973, n.d. (Box Box 23)
  - Democracy, Liberty and Property: The State Constitutional Conventions of the 1820's, 1963-1969, n.d.; (1-2 of 3 folders) (Box Box 23)
  - Democracy, Liberty and Property: The State Constztutional Conventions of the 1820's, 1963-1969, n.d.; (3 of 3 folders) (Box Box 24)
  - Great Triumvirate --Correspondence, 1973-1979, n.d. (Box Box 24)
  - Great Triumvirate --Illustrations, 1986, n.d. (Box Box 24)
  - Great Triumvirate --Ms, n.d.; (1-3 of 4 folders) (Box Box 24)
  - Great Triumvirate --Ms, n.d.; (4 of 4 folders) (Box Box 25)
  - Great Triumvirate --Notes, n.d. (Box Box 25)
  - Great Triumvirate --Notes on Calhoun, 1985, n.d. (Box Box 25)
  - Great Triumvirate --Notes on Clay, 1978-1989, n.d. (Box Box 25)
  - Great Triumvirate --TMs, n.d.; (1-3 of 9 folders) (Box Box 25)
  - Great Triumvirate --TMs, n.d.; (4-9 of 9 folders) (Box Box 26)
  - Great Triumvirate --TMs and Proof, 1989; (1-2 of 7 folders) (Box Box 26)
  - Great Triumvirate --TMs and Proof, 1989; (2-7 of 7 folders) (Box Box 27)
  - James Madison, A Biography in His Own Words, 1971-1974, n.d.; (2 folders) (Box Box 28)
  - Jefferson Image in the American Mind, 1954-1974, n.d.; (3 folders) (Box Box 28)
  - Major Crises in American History: Documentary Problems, 1959-1975; (3 folders) (Box Box 29)
  - Olive Branch and Sword: The Compromise of 1833, 1980-1984, n.d.; (2 folders) (Box Box 29)
  - Portable Thomas Jefferson, 1972-1980, n.d. (Box Box 29)
  - Thomas Jeffferson: A Profile, 1967-1979, n.d. (Box Box 29)
  - Thomas Jeffferson: A Reference Biography, 1981-1987, n.d.; (2 folders) (Box Box 30)
  - Thomas Jefferson and the American Revolution -- TMss with annotations (Box Box 30)
  - Thomas Jefferson and the New Nation, 1961-1977, n.d.; (3 folders) (Box Box 30)
  - Thomas Jefferson and the New Nation -- Ms, (1-6 of 13 folders) (Box Box 31)
  - Thomas Jefferson and the New Nation -- Ms, (7-13 of 13 folders) (Box Box 32)
  - Thomas Jefferson and the New Nation --TMs with annotations, (1-6 of 8 folders) (Box Box 33)
  - Thomas Jefferson and the New Nation --TMs with annotations, (7-8 of 8 folders) (Box Box 34)
  - Thomas Jefferson, the Founders and Constitutional Change, 1979-1985, n.d. (Box Box 34)
  - Visitors to Monticello, 1989-1990, n.d. (Box Box 34)
  - Visitors to Monticello --TMs with annotations, n.d.; (2 folders) (Box Box 34)
  - Writings, 1979-1985, n.d.; (4 folders) (Box Box 35)
- Group IV: Miscellany
  - Background Material--Bibliographical Items (Box Box 36)
  - Background Material--Merrill D. Peterson Notes, 1971-1989, n.d. (Box Box 36)
  - Background Material--Sally Hemings, 1971-1991, n.d.; (2 folders) (Box Box 36)
  - Newsclippings, 1948-1993, n.d.; (2 folders) (Box Box 36)
  - Pamphlets and Conference Handouts, 1971-1987, n.d. (Box Box 36)
  - Photographs, 1971-1986, n.d. (Box Box 37)
  - Reprints, 1852-1981, n.d.; (2 folders) (Box Box 37)
  - Unpublished Merrill D. Peterson Writings, 1946-1948. n.d.; (2 folders) (Box Box 37)